<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proviso or condition of the promises, the strait, but the straight-way that leadeth unto happiness being the substance of two sermons preached at Wilton, March the first, 1656, upon 2 Cor. 7. 1. : now published at the request of some of the parishioners and auditors then present / by Tho. Drayton ...</title>
            <author>Drayton, Thomas, d. 1658?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277151</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 625:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proviso or condition of the promises, the strait, but the straight-way that leadeth unto happiness being the substance of two sermons preached at Wilton, March the first, 1656, upon 2 Cor. 7. 1. : now published at the request of some of the parishioners and auditors then present / by Tho. Drayton ...</title>
                  <author>Drayton, Thomas, d. 1658?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, VII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58489:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Proviſo or Condition OF THE PROMISES, The Strait, but the Straight-way that leadeth unto Happineſs. Being the Subſtance of Two SERMONS Preached at <hi>Wilton, March</hi> the Firſt. 1656. Upon 2 COR. 7.1. Now publiſhed at the requeſt of ſome of the Pariſhioners and Auditors then preſent:</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Tho. Drayton,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in Divinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb.</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:58489:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58489:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Proviſo or Condition OF THE PROMISES: The Strait, but the Straight-way that leadeth unto Happineſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 COR. 7.1.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes, dearly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the fear of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat this Text is a Concluſion or Inference, out of the Apoſtles former Conference or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, none that obſerve that Illative note <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>therefore,</hi> will deny. And as the three laſt Verſes of the former Chapter, are an Introduction to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58489:3"/> this; ſo it is a Genuine Deduction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, in which (the Illative Particle ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part) we have two general parts.</p>
            <p>The firſt is a loving and a winning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Beloved,</hi> or <hi>Dearly Beloved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is an Apoſtolical Impoſition or Charge, <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with the firſt of theſe; It is ſaid of <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.19. That the Lord <hi>did let none of his words fall to the ground;</hi> ſo will I not paſs over any one word in the Text un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dearly Beloved:</hi> This title the Apoſtle uſeth not complementally nor formally, but in reality and truth; for theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> were intirely beloved of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> not with the common love onely, which we ow to all men, but with a ſpecial affection; and that upon a threefold accompt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As they were born and begotten from above.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58489:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. As they were his Spiritual Brethren, and Fellow-members in Chriſt. And</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they were his own Off-ſpring, and the Fruits of his labor in the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. <hi>For in Christ Jeſus I have begotten you through the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence we have two Inſtructions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there are not onely Natural but Spiritual Relations to be found among men, eſpecially in the Church and Congregation of the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. <hi>I write not theſe things to ſhame you, but as my beloved ſons I warn you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That this Spiritual Conſanguinity, is or ſhould be as effectual to beget mutual and reciprocal affection, as the natural affinity is, yea, far more forcible. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1. Every one that loveth him that begat, loveth him that is begotten of him.</p>
            <p>And here he ſaith, <hi>Dearly Beloved,</hi> but paſs we now from the Compellation to the Impoſition, wherein the Apoſtle doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the truth of his love unto them in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In minding them of the antecedent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58489:4"/> promiſes, ſet down in the cloſe of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Chapter, <hi>Having therefore theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In exciting them to eye, obſerve, and fulfil the condition of the ſame, leſt they ſhould come ſhort of them in the end; <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> Our Apoſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.10. of his former Epiſtle, tells us, That according to the grace of God which was given unto him he as a wiſe Maſter-builder had laid the Foundation, and that another buildeth thereupon: But let every man take heed how he buildeth thereupon. The former part of that Verſe he hath verified as elſwhere, ſo in this Text; the latter part which is the Caution, lieth upon my ſelf, and all other Miniſters in theſe days, to look unto it; namely, what, and how, we build upon this Foundation.</p>
            <p>In this part of the Text then we have two ſubordinate Members; the Apoſtles ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes;</hi> and then his ſuperſtructure, <hi>Let us cleanſe our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58489:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit;</hi> or theſe two. A true ſuppoſition, <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes;</hi> and then an advice, impoſition, and injunction, <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves, &amp;c.</hi> Or in plain terms, the Apoſtle's Doctrine, and the uſe which he makes of it; the former being matter of Grace and Promiſe; the latter, matter of Command and Duty. Of which, the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work is firſt to be ſurveyed, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This part of the Text we may call the Believers Patrimony, or rather his evidence for that which he hopeth for, and is to ſeek after, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. Faith is ſaid to be the ground or ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence or demonſtration of things not ſeen; which is eſpecially <hi>ratione objecti,</hi> in regard of the promiſes on which it is built. In this then are three particulars to be ſeriouſly viewed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The intereſt of Believers, or of the yong itinerant Saints, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>theſe promiſes.</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſons that have ſpecial intereſt in them, to wit, Converts and Believing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58489:5"/> Saints; ſuch as theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> were.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What intereſt theſe have therein for the preſent.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, we may here take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the beſt intereſt that the yong Saints have for all manner of bleſſings, not yet enjoyed, are the rich, precious, and moſt infallible promiſes of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. Theſe all died in the Faith, not having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the promiſes; but having ſeen them afar off, and were perſwaded of them.</p>
            <p n="2">And 2. whereas the promiſes of God are of two ſorts, concerning either Corporal or Spiritual things, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>But godlineſs is profitable unto all things, having a promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> We may note, that the Spiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes (ſuch as theſe are, to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates) are the greateſt promiſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promiſes, that by them we ſhould or might be made partakers of the Divine Nature, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through luſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58489:5"/>
            <p n="3">3. Obſerve, that among many Spiritual promiſes (thoſe to which our Apoſtle here refers us) are not the meaneſt or the leaſt, as is implied in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is here not onely a Relative, but a Demonſtrative Noune or Pronoune. Now then to take them in the order of nature; firſt, it carrieth us back to the promiſe of Reception. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. of the former Chapter, <hi>And I will receive you;</hi> Where the Apoſtle ſeemeth to look back to <hi>Jere</hi> 3.14. and other ſuch like places. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, He tranſmits us to <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. where the Lord ſaith, <hi>That he will be our God, and we ſhall be his people;</hi> according to <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Jere.</hi> 31.33. and many other places of that import: Thirdly, He leads us back to the 18 <hi>Verſe,</hi> where the Lord promiſeth to be our Father, and to take us for his Sons and Daughters, according to <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.6. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.10. This word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>theſe,</hi> is alſo Signal or Demonſtrative, and ſets forth the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the phraſes in theſe particulars. Firſt, In the Author of them, who is ſaid to be Almighty, <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. and therefore able to perform; and in <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. he is ſtiled
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58489:6"/> 
               <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or the Lord that changeth not. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, In regard of the great things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, or the contents of the promiſes, of which you heard before: Unto which, two great Dignities and Prerogatives more are to be added out of <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. That God hath promiſed to ſet his Sanctuary in us, and to make us his Temple, according to <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.11. And ſecondly, to make us his Garden <hi>Eden</hi> or Paradiſe, in that he hath promiſed to walk in us: A third remarkable thing is, the extent of theſe promiſes, That they are made not onely to the Males, but the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males alſo; <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. and the laſt thing not to be paſſed over without due obſervation and regard, is the condition of the promiſes, upon which they were made: <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you;</hi> which is the ſum of <hi>Pauls</hi> injunction and charge here in our Text.</p>
            <p>Thus of the Intereſt it ſelf, <hi>theſe promiſes;</hi> the perſons intereſted are, as you ſee, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian</hi> Saints, and all ſuch as were converted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58489:6"/> to God, believed in his Son, and were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed and waſhed through him inwardly, as well as outwardly: For the promiſe is made to you and your children, and to all that are afar of, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call. For the third, the kinde, meaſure, or degree of Intereſt, which theſe perſons have; it is not for the moſt part actual poſſeſſion, and ſenſe or feeling grounded thereupon; but a true claim and title thereunto, and a ſuitable hope, ſo far as they do or intend to obſerve the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24,25. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.12. Not as though I had already attained, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. before alleadged.</p>
            <p>Thus of the ground-work; now of the Apoſtles ſuperſtructure, <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> From which words we may in the general learn theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the promiſes of God are not onely a foundation of our Faith, Hope, and Comfort; but are, or ſhould be, a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work of our obedience, and a moſt effectual incentive or motive unto duty, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58489:7"/> 
               <hi>Honor thy Father and Mother, which is the first Commandment with promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That in Gods promiſes, which are conditional (as all theſe are) we muſt not onely have an eye upon what is promiſed, but a ſharp regard alſo upon what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. The condition as well as the donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the promiſes muſt be heeded, regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obſerved.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas this charge here tends unto, and ends in the work of Sanctification, let us take notice, That the great exigence and requiring of the promiſes at our hands, is the carrying on, and finiſhing of the great, holy, and moſt neceſſary work of our Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4. For this is the Will of God, even your Sanctification. It is that whereunto we were elected, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. and called, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7. But to come to a more particular conſideration of the condition, which is the main thing inſiſted upon in this Text; in it we have a twofold Chriſtian duty, and both of the greateſt importance, injoyned unto us, and charged upon us; the firſt in theſe words, <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58489:7"/> from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit:</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in theſe, <hi>Perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> Of which, we ſhall crave leave to ſpeak in this order; Firſt, by way of Analyſis and Expoſition; Secondly, by way of Doctrine &amp; Propoſition; and thirdly, by way of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to our ſelves, or of Uſe and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. All which ſhall be grounded upon clear and evident teſtimony of Scripture.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe injunctions or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges laid upon us; in it are four things to be opened, the firſt is the evil which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, <hi>All filthineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit;</hi> the ſecond is the perſons from whom it is to be ſeparated, <hi>Our ſelves;</hi> the third is by what kinde of act, <hi>By cleanſing the ſame out;</hi> and the fourth is the perſons that are to be engaged in this work, <hi>Let us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The evil to be removed, is not the evil of puniſhment for ſin, but the evil of ſin, the root and ſpring of all our miſery; it is here called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, inquinament or pollution; By which word we are not onely to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the open ſin, but the falſe holineſs alſo; which is not preſcribed by the Lord, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58489:8"/> choſen and ſet up by men: All which is not onely filthy in the concrete, but filthineſs in the Abſtract, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.6. <hi>But we are all as an unclean thing, and all our righteouſneſſes are as filthy rags; and we all do fade like a Leafe, and our iniquities like the wind have taken us away</hi> This filthineſs is here ſet forth by a diſtribution of it into its ſpecies, according to a twofold ſubject, <hi>The filthineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit.</hi> Where we may obſerve, Firſt, That there is not onely a pollution of the fleſh to be found; ſuch as lying, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, curſing, gluttony, drunkenneſs, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, whoredom, coveteouſneſs, theft, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſuch like groſs and manifeſt ſins are; but a filthineſs of the ſpirit alſo, whereby the Devils are denominated unclean ſpirits; ſuch as high-flying thoughts, ſerpentine wiſdom, hypocriſie, and ſeeming holineſs, pride, and arrogancy, ſelf-love, ſelf-ſeeking, ſtrife and debate, factiouſneſs, wrath, revenge, malice, cruelty, miſchievouſneſs, perſecution, and heart-murder, ſpiritual whoredom, and the like. Secondly, take notice from hence, That man conſiſting not onely of a body
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58489:8"/> which is fleſh, but of an immortal ſpirit, is ſince the fall, ſubject to ſins of both kindes (which the Devils themſelves are not) till by. Grace they be wholly waſhed away. In this evil to be removed, we are alſo to attend the meaſure and degree, in which it is to be removed <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all filthineſs; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Dead flies cauſe the Apothecaries ointment to ſend forth a ſtinking ſavor; ſo doth a little folly, him that is in reputation for wiſdom and honor.</hi> Thus of the evil to be removed; the perſons from whom we are to remove it, are not our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren onely, but our ſelves in the firſt place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Thou hypocrite, firſt cast out the beam that is in thine own eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the mote that is in thy Brothers eye;</hi> For <hi>every one of us muſt give an account of himſelf unto God, Rom.</hi> 14.12. The act to be imployed in this removal of the evil, is the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let us cleanſe or purifie our ſelves;</hi> whereof the legal waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, purifications, and cleanſings were a type. So that a bare confeſſion of our ſins, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailment of them, a loathing of them, and a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58489:9"/> purpoſe to leave them; though theſe be good ſteps and degrees towards this act and duty, yet they all fall ſhort of what is here required, and propoſed of the true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Saints, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. The fourth and laſt thing to be opened, is the perſons who are here to be engaged, and vigorouſly ſet on work; to wit, all that have any remainders of inward or outward filthineſs left in them, even they that in a good meaſure are purified already; ſuch as theſe Saints of <hi>Corinth</hi> were.</p>
            <p>Thus far by way of Expoſition; now the Propoſition and Doctrine upon the whole, is this, That all they that would have an intereſt and ſhare in the precious promiſes aforeſaid, muſt <hi>Cleanſe themſelves of all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both of the fleſh and of the ſpirit.</hi> This Doctrine is not mine, but the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſly here and elſwhere, as you will ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none; and not his onely, but the Doctrine of the Prophets, of the Apoſtles, and of Chriſt himſelf; witneſs theſe enſuing Scriptures. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58489:9"/> ceaſe to do evil.</hi> Iſa. 57 11. <hi>Depart ye, depart ye; go ye from thence, touch no unclean thing; go ye out of the midst of her, be ye clean ye that bear the Veſſels of the Lord.</hi> Jere 4.14. <hi>Waſh thine heart, O</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>that thou maiſt be ſaved: How long ſhall thy wicked thoughts lodg in thee?</hi> Jere. 13.27. <hi>Wo unto thee, O</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>wilt not thou be made clean? O when ſhall it once be?</hi> Ezek. 18.31. <hi>Caſt away all your tranſgreſſions whereby you have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit; for why will ye die, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael? 1 Pet. 2.1. <hi>Wherefore lay aſide all malice (or naughtineſs) and all guile and hypocriſies, and evil ſurmiſings, and all evil ſpeakings.</hi> Jam. 1.21. <hi>Wherefore laying aſide all filthineſs, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, receive with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the ingrafted word which is able to ſave your ſouls.</hi> Jam. 3.6. <hi>Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you; cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and purifie your hearts ye double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded.</hi> Matth. 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they</hi> (and they onely) <hi>ſhall ſee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is there leſs ground both of Reaſon &amp; Equity, then Evidence of Scripture, for this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58489:10"/> duty; Firſt, in regard of the miſchievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that which is to be removed; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in regard of him that requireth it; and thirdly, in reſpect of the ſufficiency of help afforded unto us by the Lord, for that purpoſe; and laſtly, that we of right ſhould have a concurrent hand therein.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe; firſt conſider what all ſin and unrighteouſneſs is in Gods ſight; it is pollution and filthineſs it ſelf. <hi>Ezek</hi> 24.13. Hence it is compared to every filthy and abominable thing, as to the gorge and vomit of drunkards. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 28.8. To the ſcum of a Pot. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.6,12. To the mire where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Sow walloweth. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. To the vomit of a dog, there. To the whoredoms of a Strumpet. <hi>Jere.</hi> 13.27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. To the abomination of Idols. <hi>Ezek</hi> 36.25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is a ſuperfluous thing that men may well ſpare. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Wherefore put away all filthineſs and ſuperfluity of vaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is of an infectious, contagious and ſpreading nature. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6,7. <hi>Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58489:10"/>
            <p>Fourthly, It excludes us from entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem. Rev.</hi> 21.27. <hi>And there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, There is no forgiveneſs of ſin until they be left and put away from us, whatſoever men may dream to the contrary. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.16,17,18. <hi>Waſh you, make you clean, put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well; ſeek judgment, relieve the oppreſſed, judg the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, plead for the Widow. Come now and let us reaſon together, ſaith the Lord: Though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be white as Snow; though they be red as crimſon, they ſhall be white as wool.</hi> Jere. 33.8. <hi>And I will cleanſe them from all their iniquity, whereby they have ſinned againſt me: And I will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all their iniquity, whereby they have ſinned, and whereby they have tranſgreſſed againſt me;</hi> for the cauſe muſt be taken away ere the effect can ceaſe. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.13.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, That even the Law as well as the Goſpel, declares the wrath of God againſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58489:11"/> all ſin whatſoever. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>For the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven against all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men who withhold the truth in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the ſecond place, he that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth this total removal of ſin, is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary nature unto it, and cannot poſſibly have any communion with it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.20. <hi>Shall the throne of iniquity have fellowſhip with thee?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14,15. [For what fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip hath righteouſneſs with unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and what communion hath light with darkneſs; and what concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Belial?</hi>] <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. [Thou art of purer eyes then to behold evil, and canſt not look on iniquity]</p>
            <p>In the third place, the Lord doth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afford us ſpace and time to get this work done. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21. [And I gave her ſpace to repent, and ſhe repented not,] but ſufficient means alſo for our thorough cleanſing ſo. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. [Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and you ſhall be clean from all your filthineſs; and from all your idols will I cleanſe you:] Which promiſed water
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58489:11"/> is not onely the pure water, and doctrine of his Word. <hi>John</hi> 15.3. [Now are ye clean through the Word which I have ſpoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.] <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. [That he might ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and waſh it with water through the Word;] but the promiſed Spirit of Chriſt alſo, which ſometimes is called the Blood of the Covenant, becauſe it was figured forth by Blood in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.6,7,8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.20. <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.23,24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.14. Sometimes it is compared to fire. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 4.4. [When the Lord ſhall have waſhed the filth of the Daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> and purged away the blood of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the ſpirit of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſpirit of burning:] And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to water, as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.3. [I will pour water upon him that is thirſty, and a flood upon the dry ground: I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed, and my bleſſing upon thine Off-ſpring:] And ſometimes to Fullers Sope. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2. [For he is like the Refiners fire, and Fullers ſope:] This is expreſly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſt; ſo that we neither want wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor ſope, to make a thorow cleanſing or purgation of our ſelves from ſins.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58489:12"/>
            <p>For this is the Fountain which the Lord hath opened to the houſe of <hi>David</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for ſin and for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, it is but meet that we which had a hand in polluting and defiling our ſelves, ſhould be imployed and engaged in the purging our ſelves; and ſo much the rather, becauſe it is for our own good and everlaſting welfare.</p>
            <p>Thus of the words by way of Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Now by way of Tranſpoſition and Uſe, the Truth and Equity of this Doctrine being thus cleared up, what remains but that we ſhould make our beſt advantage of it? For whatſoever things were written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, they were written for our inſtruction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then by way of Information, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent from hence, That as nothing is ſo offenſive and contrary to God, and his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, as ſin is; ſo there is no greater bar and obſtruction, then iniquity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs is, to keep us from the benefit of all his promiſes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in this point ſome of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58489:12"/> writers in <hi>Europe,</hi> are much degenerated from the Doctrine of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14,15,16. is to be underſtood onely of Babes in Chriſt. Secondly, this Doctrine ſerves to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute many common errors and miſtakes; and firſt, that opinion or aſſertion, That ſin can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wholly ſubdued in the Saints, by the Grace and Truth of Chriſt, while they live in the Mortal Body; for if that cannot be attained, the deſign of the Father, who gave his Son, that he might deſtroy the workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. is diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Chriſts love towards men is made of none effect; who loved us and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for us, that he might ſanctifie and waſh us with the waſhing of water by the Word, and preſent us unto himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrincle, or any ſuch thing. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.24,25,26,27. Yea, the condition of the promiſes being impoſſible to be performed, ſhould be unjuſt, and the promiſes made of none effect; but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as many places in the Old Teſtament are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58489:13"/> brought to plead for the continuance in ſin, as 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.20. To thoſe we may anſwer with the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19. That the Law made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did, by which we draw nigh unto God. And for the Scriptures alleadged out of the New Teſtament, that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24,25. can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood of <hi>Pauls</hi> preſent eſtate; for the ſecond Verſe of Chapter eight, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts it, as doth alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16,17. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. but muſt onely be underſtood as was ſaid before, of the Babes and Yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in Chriſt; ſo muſt that alſo be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. and that 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, if it be compared with Verſe the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and fourteenth of the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; or with Verſe third of the third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and with Verſe the ſeventeenth of the fourth Chapter; laſtly, That of <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. can in reaſon be no more underſtood of him, and his Fellow-Apoſtles, where he ſaith, That in many things we offend all, then that which he ſpeaks plurally alſo Verſe 9. Therewith bleſs we God, even the Father, (to wit, with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58489:13"/> the tongue) and therewith curſe we men which are made after the ſimilitude of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This giveth a check to their Error, who ſay, That in death (when we put off the Body of Clay) all ſin ſhall be put off and mortified, and not before: For firſt it is by the Spirit, that the deeds of the body or fleſh muſt be mortified, and not the ſinful deeds of the ſpirit by the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. Secondly, If the natural death healed all ſins, none would die in their ſins, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour threatens, that the unbelieving Jews ſhould do, <hi>John</hi> 8.21,24. Laſtly, We are commanded to cleanſe our ſelves from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of the fleſh, and of the ſpirit; and this is to be done in our life time, and not to be done in our days of our death: And by this opinion, Corporal death ſhould effect more, then the Spirit of Grace could do all our life long, in the final mortification of our ſins.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This may confute them, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That Chriſt came to take away the guilt of our ſins by his death, and ſuffering be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58489:14"/> the act or corruption is taken away; for the cauſe muſt be taken away before the effect, as we ſaid before and proved out of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.16,17,18. <hi>Jere.</hi> 33.8. to which you may adde, Chap. 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. For through the Blood of his Croſs, in due time he taketh away the guilt of ſins repented of, left, and put away; yet the Spirit of Grace, which is the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, muſt firſt ſanctifie us, and cleanſe us therefrom, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. alſo <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.29. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.20,21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This may ſtop the mouths of them which ſay, we do not read, That ever any man yet was cleanſed wholly from ſin; to which we Reply, That if this were not, men themſelves, and not the Grace of God, were in default; but there is an <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who are of a clean heart, <hi>Pſal</hi> 73.1. Who are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the world, and the world to them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14,15,16. In whoſe Spirit there is no guile, and conſequently no ſin, for all ſin is deceitful; ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22. Yea, <hi>John</hi> ſaw a numberleſs number of thoſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9,10,14. So alſo <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.4. Theſe are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58489:14"/> the <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of which we read <hi>Num.</hi> 23.21. and <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.14,15.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It meets with that diſtinction more common then commendable; that though ſin muſt not reign in us, yet it muſt remain in us while we are here: For firſt, as long as it remains in us, it will oppoſe the work of God, and get the victory at times, if not with our will, yet againſt our will. Secondly, If all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit muſt be purged out of us, how can it remain? do the ſpots or filth remain in clothes, when they are cleanſed there from? did not Chriſt come to ſanctifie and waſh us, that he might preſent us without ſpot or wrincle, or any ſuch thing unto himſelf? Surely this and other diſtinctions, that plead for the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry continuance of ſin in us, cannot come from above; but ſince they hinder the work of the Lord, muſt needs originally come from Hell, and the Devil; though ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons otherwiſe zealous and vertuouſly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have at unawares, received and uſed the ſame, without conſidering the hurt and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that followeth thereupon. See <hi>Jere.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58489:15"/> 50.20. <hi>In thoſe days, and in that time, ſaith the Lord, the iniquity of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be ſought for, and there ſhall be none, and the ſins of</hi> Judah, <hi>and they ſhall not be found; for I will ſpare them which are left. Mic.</hi> 7.19. Sheweth how God will deal with the ſins and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his people, as he did with the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> he will firſt ſubdue, and then drown them: Alſo <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.13. he promiſes, That the remnant of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall not utter iniquity, nor ſpeak lies: And <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3. That Chriſt <hi>ſhall ſit as a refiner and a purifier of ſilver, and he ſhall purifie the ſons of</hi> Levi, <hi>and purge them as gold and ſilver, that they may offer unto him an offering in righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thus much of the Uſe of Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; now by way of Correction.</p>
            <p>This Propoſition or Doctrine ſerves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove four ſorts of men among others: Firſt, Thoſe who have cleanſed themſelves from many outward ſins of the fleſh, but are not purified from the ſins of the ſpirit; as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pride, wrath, uncharitable cenſuring, envy, and the like. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.12. <hi>There is a generation that is pure in their own eyes, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58489:15"/> yet are not waſhed from their filthineſs:</hi> So <hi>Matth</hi> 23.25,26. <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites; for ye make clean the outſide of the cup, and of the platter, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, they are full of extortion and exceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It reprehends thoſe yet more ſecretly who rely upon the promiſe of God, and look to have their ſhare therein, and yet wittingly and willingly continue in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs both of fleſh and ſpirit: See <hi>Jere.</hi> 7.8,9,13, alſo 27. To theſe it may be ſaid, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake to <hi>Simon Magus, Acts</hi> 8.21,22. <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy heart is not right in the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This yet more condemns their folly; who knowing that they muſt repent, and be cleanſed, ere they can be ſaved; yet not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protract the time for ſo great a work, but daily pollute and defile themſelves, contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more filthineſs then that which they had before, and making their ſtains and ſpots of a deeper dye, and harder to be waſhed out.</p>
            <p>Finally, This may ſerve for the horror or terror of thoſe who having for a time begun to reform themſelves, and put away their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58489:16"/> ſins, yet return again with the Dog to the vomit, and with the Sow to her wallowing in the mire; ſee 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.18,19,20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. <hi>In thy filthineſs is leudneſs, becauſe I have purged thee, and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſs any more, until I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Uſe of this Doctrine, is for Exhortation: Firſt, To all ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this firſt condition of the promiſes, ſo clearly ſet down, Verſe 17. of the former Chapter, and here in the Text, and what is required thereby.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To examine how far we have proceeded in fulfilling the ſame. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſins?</hi> I fear very few.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To thoſe that have begun the work, that they go on forward to finiſh it. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11. <hi>He that is unjuſt, let him be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſtill; and he that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill; but he that is righteous, let him be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſtill;</hi> that is more and more. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2,3. <hi>Beloved, now are we the children of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58489:16"/> yet it doth not appear what we ſhall be; but we know, That when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is: For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf as he is pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, To thoſe that have not begun this great important and moſt neceſſary work, to fall upon it forthwith: <hi>O waſh you, make you clean,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.16,17,18. otherwiſe you cannot have your ſins forgiven you; yea, <hi>Waſh your hearts, that ye may be ſaved,</hi> Jere. 4.14. <hi>Cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your hearts, ye double minded; be afflicted and mourn, and weep; for your laughter ſhall be turned into mourning, and your joy into heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Humble your ſelves in the ſight of God, and he ſhall lift you up, Jam</hi> 4.8,9,10. Ye ſay that ye relie upon Chriſt, but what part hath Chriſt with <hi>Belial?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. Therefore <hi>let every one that nameth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, depart from iniquity,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. See what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.3,4,5. <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the Hill of the Lord? And who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? He that hath clean hands, and a pure heart; who hath not lift up
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58489:17"/> his ſoul to vanity, nor ſworn deceitfully: He</hi> (and he onely) <hi>ſhall receive the bleſſing from the Lord, even righteouſneſs from the God of his ſalvation.</hi> Therefore mortifie your mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers upon earth, fornication, uncleanneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, affection, evil-concupiſcence and covetouſneſs, which is idolatry; for which things ſake, the wrath of God cometh upon the children of diſobedience; ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19,20,21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.21.</p>
            <p>Take to you the Water, the Water of the Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9. <hi>Wherewith ſhall a yong man cleanſe his way, by taking heed thereunto, according to thy Word.</hi> Seek Sope of Chriſt, yea, Fullers ſope, to be baptiſed with the Holy Ghoſt, and with fire, <hi>Mal</hi> 3.2. <hi>Walk in the Light, as Chriſt is in the Light, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall purge you from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. Let us follow the practice of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29. who cauſed all the filth of the Temple to be carried out, and that houſe to be purged and ſanctified, that the holy Service of God might be renewed therein.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58489:17"/>
            <p>Thus of the firſt duty or Chriſtian courſe, required in the Condition or Proviſo of the Promiſes; now follows the other in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> In which, by way of Analyſis, we have two parts; firſt, a work of renovation or perfection, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holineſs: The ſecond is the kinde of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the poſture or principle, in which and out of which it muſt be done, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the fear of God.</hi> For the former of theſe, in it are theſe particulars to be explained, ere we come to the Doctrine or Propoſition it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The object or ſubject thing to be perfected, <hi>holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the act required at our hands, in relation thereunto, <hi>perfecting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The perſons to be engaged in that act likewiſe, <hi>let us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, It is not here the Sanctification of fleſh and blood, which is proud of its ſelf, and contemptuous of others. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.5. <hi>Which ſay, Stand by thy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58489:18"/> ſelf, come not near me, for I am holier then thou.</hi> Which how ſpecious ſoever it may ſeem, it is but hypocriſie before the Lord, and an abomination in his ſight, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.12. alſo 16.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. For that which is eſteemed highly among men, is an abomination before the Lord; for this holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be changed for a better, but cannot any way be perfected: Nor is this holineſs a ceremonial holineſs, which was but a figure of the true; but in ſhort, it is that which is called Gods own holineſs, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. Not onely becauſe he commands it, but it is that way wherein he walketh, the holineſs which he communicateth, and whereby the Saints are denominated holy ones; of which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Chap.</hi> 35.8. <hi>And an high-way ſhall be there, and a way, and it ſhall be called the way of holineſs; the unclean ſhall not paſs over it, but it ſhall be for thoſe; the wayfaring-men, though fools, ſhall not erre therein.</hi> This is that holineſs that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Houſe of God for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.5. Which holineſs is either a way and race, to wit, an holy courſe of obedience in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58489:18"/> the Will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. <hi>But now ye have your fruits unto holineſs, and the end everlaſting life. Heb.</hi> 10.36. Or elſe it is the inward holineſs of Gods Image and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, from whence that obedience proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.34. <hi>And that ye put on the new man, which is created after God in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and holineſs of truth.</hi> Both which, if they be not coincident, yet concur to one effect, the purging out of all iniquity. So that this laſt duty ſeems to be required in order to the former, and both in reſpect of the promiſes.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond particular, the act here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies not onely to go about a thing, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.32. and to execute it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6,11. but to finiſh and to adde the end to the beginning. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6. And ſo here the Participle here uſed, ſignifieth a profection with a tendency to a perfection. As for the word <hi>perfection,</hi> it is variouſly uſed, and there is a manifold perfection ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of among men; one of profeſſion and outward ſtate among the Papiſts; and ſo they will have their religious men, eſpecially
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58489:19"/> thoſe in orders, to be termed perfect men, if any will indulge them that honor and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and another of the inward ſtate, which we are here to underſtand; that again is manifold; one of ſincerity and uprightneſs: So King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> pleads for himſelf, That he had walked before the Lord in truth, and with a perfect heart, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38.3. But this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is not ſufficient, or always to be reſted in. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Seeing ye have purified your ſouls in obeying the truth, through the ſpirit, unto unfeigned or ſincere love of the Brethren: See that ye love one another with a pure heart fervently.</hi> See 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>A ſecond perfection there is of parts, when all the ſeveral graces of Gods ſanctifying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are found in a man. This is conceived to be in every Convert or Believer. But the truth thereof may be juſtly queſtioned; for ſome want humility, ſome meekneſs, ſome patience, and the like; And why doth St. <hi>Peter</hi> command us to adde to our Faith. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; to Vertue, Knowledge; to Knowledge, Temperance; to Temperance, Patience; to Patience, Godlineſs; to Godlineſs, Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58489:19"/> kindneſs; to Brotherly kindneſs, Love. If we have all theſe at our firſt converſion? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5,6,7.</p>
            <p>A third is the perfection of degrees, when holineſs in a full degree is by us attained an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the Law of God: And this is threefold, according to a threefold eſtate or diſpenſation. The firſt is of love to God above all, and to our Neighbor as to our ſelves, which is the ſum and fulfilling of the Law and the Prophets; to the putting down of all contrary diſpoſitions: This is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection enjoyned by the Apoſtle, <hi>Col</hi> 3.14. <hi>and above all put on Love, which is the Bond of perfection.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. This is called <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio viae,</hi> and allowed of by all the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The ſecond is a greater perfection and power in all love and goodneſs, when Chriſt in the power of his Reſurrection, ariſeth in the Saints, after they are wholly dead with him to ſin. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.5. For if we have been planted into Chriſt, with the likeneſs of his death, we ſhall alſo in the likeneſs of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. This is that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he had not attained unto, when he wrote to the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58489:20"/> 
               <hi>Philippiane,</hi> Chap. 3.11,12. And yet even then he was able to do all things, <hi>viz.</hi> that were commanded through Chriſt which ſtrengthens him, Chap. 4.12,13. Howbeit he hoped for the other, even while he was <hi>viator,</hi> or in the body.</p>
            <p>The third is <hi>perfectio patriae,</hi> the higheſt perfection of the Saints, of which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>And to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of just men made perfect.</hi> Here in the Text, we underſtand the firſt of theſe three laſt named, which is an imperfect eſtate gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually in compariſon of the ſecond, as the ſecond is being parallel'd with the third; yet ſome there be who in this Text underſtand the ſecond alſo; which without doubt we ſhould both hope for, and pray for, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelves thereunto. By the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and by both the former, we ſhould ſeek after the third; in all which, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled through Chriſt, but according to ſeveral diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and degrees: For in the firſt, we have communion with Chriſt, according to the fleſh, or in a lower and weaker way: In the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58489:20"/> ſecond with Chriſt according to the Spirit, in a more lively and powerful way in the ſimilitude of his Reſurrection, wherein he walked with his Diſciples forty days upon Earth: And in the third, with Chriſt after his Aſcenſion and Glorification; yet the leaſt of theſe is an holy Perfection.</p>
            <p>For the perſons to be engaged, they are all thoſe that have not yet attained to that ſtate; for he that made us without our ſelves, will not ſave us without our beſt endeavors and concurrences; we have alſo had a hand in fulfilling the meaſure of our diſobedience and depravation; and the Lord may juſtly engage us in the work of new obedience, and the renewing of his Image and Kingdom in us; as he doth here and elſwhere fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently.</p>
            <p>The whole Propoſition or Doctrine then is this, That thoſe who would be made heirs and partakers of the Divine Promiſes, muſt perfect the race of holy Obedience ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and the holy Image of God, which is to be renewed in them, or they muſt put on that love which is the Bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58489:21"/> and the fulfilling of the Law, as hath been ſaid: Nor is our Apoſtle herein ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and preciſe above other his Fellow-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Meſſengers of God; nor goeth he higher then Chriſt himſelf did in his expreſs Commands: For as <hi>Moſes</hi> witneſſeth, the Lord required this of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Believers, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>And when</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>was ninety years old and nine, the Lord appeared unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>and ſaid unto him, I am the Almighty God, walk thou before me, and be perſect.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf requireth as much of all <hi>Iſrael. And now, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, and to walk in all his ways, and to love him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God, with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoul?</hi> And <hi>Levit</hi> 19.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbor as thy ſelf; I am the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt be perfect with the Lord thy God.</hi> So our Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9. <hi>And this we wiſh, even your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> Yea, he injoyneth perfection unto them in his farewel, Verſe 11. <hi>Finally, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren farewel: Be perfect, be of good comfort,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58489:21"/> be of one minde, live in peace, and the God of love and peace ſhall be with you:</hi> So <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, let us go on to perfection.</hi> Jam. 1.4. <hi>But let patience have her perfect work in you, that ye may be perfect and intire, wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Chap. 2.8. <hi>If ye ſhall fulfil the Royal Law, according to the Scripture, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbor as thy ſelf, you do well.</hi> Yea, Chriſt himſelf doth not onely commend love to God and men, unto us as the fulfilling of the Law and the Prophets, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.36,37,38,39. but he expreſly commands us to be perfect as our heavenly Father is perfect, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48.</p>
            <p>Nor is there leſs reaſon or equity for this part of the Charge and Condition, then there was for the former; For firſt, God who is holy, and love it ſelf, and perfect in holineſs and love, hath predeſtinated us to be made conformable unto the Image of his Son, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Who is the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs Image of his perſon, Heb.</hi> 1.3. And the genuine Son of the Father, in Truth and Love, 2 <hi>Epiſt. John</hi> 3.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58489:22"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>He hath choſen us in him, before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love, Eph.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This holineſs in love, is that whereunto we are called; 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7. <hi>For God hath not called us unto uncleanneſs, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holineſs, Col.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Holy love to God and men, is that which we ow to him for his love unto us in Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 116.1. <hi>I love the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. For the love of Chriſt conſtraineth us, becauſe we thus judg, that if one died for all, then were all dead, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. to 16.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is through holineſs and love, that all ſin muſt be overcome and buried in us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.8. <hi>And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, have fervent love among your ſelves; for love ſhall cover the multitude of ſins;</hi> yea, all ſins whatſoever, as <hi>Solomon</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth in theſe words, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Hatred ſtirreth up ſtrife, but love covereth all ſin;</hi> and that in a burying way firſt, or in mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58489:22"/>
            <p>Sixthly, The Law of God (whoſe fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and accompliſhment ſtandeth in love) is eſtabliſhed in Heaven for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5,6,7,8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.89. inſomuch, <hi>That Heaven and Earth ſhall ſooner paſs away, then one jot or tittle of the Law ſhall go unfulfilled, Matth.</hi> 5.18. Which fulfilling muſt be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not onely by Chriſt for us, but by him and us joyntly. Alſo <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.15. For he ſaith unto <hi>John, Thus it becometh us to fulfil all righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, There is no other way left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us in Chriſt, that leadeth to life, but the keeping of the Commandments through his grace and help. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Matth. 19,17. <hi>But if thou wilt enter into life, keep the Commandments.</hi> Rev. 22.14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his Commandments, that they may have right to the Tree of Life, and enter through the Gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, God hath not left us deſtitute, either of outward or inward means, for the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58489:23"/> fulfilling and accompliſhment of the Law; and the love, holineſs and righteouſneſs which it requireth: For firſt, as to outward means, the Apoſtle ſpeaks thus. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16,17. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for redargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for correction, and for inſtruction in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; That the man of God may be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and throughly furniſhed unto all good works. Eph.</hi> 4.11,12,13. [And he gave ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and ſome Paſtors, and Teachers; for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, and for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt: Till we all come in the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Faith, and the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.] And for inward means, [Chriſt is the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake, to every one that believeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4.] And that as otherwife, ſo that through his Grace and Spirit [the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8,4.]</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58489:23"/>
            <p>Ninthly, God hath not onely promiſed to put his Law into our inward parts, and to write it in our hearts, <hi>Jere.</hi> 31.33,34. <hi>Ezek</hi> 36.25,26,27. but hath expreſly engaged himſelf to work ſo much love in us, as the Law any where requireth. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. [And the Lord thy God ſhall circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy Seed, to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, that thou maiſt live.]</p>
            <p>Tenthly, God is willing and ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his work unto the end, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6,7.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, Chriſt hath not onely taught us to pray for a perfect obedience to Gods will in this Petition, <hi>Thy will be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> but he himſelf (who in all things was heard of his Father) hath pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our perfection in love. <hi>John</hi> 17.20,21,22,23. [Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo that ſhall believe on me through their word: That they all may be one, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us: That the world may believe, that thou haſt ſent me; and the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58489:24"/> given them, that they may be one, even as we are one; I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one, and that the world may know that thou haſt ſent me, and haſt loved them, as thou haſt loved me.]</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The work which God hath given us to do, muſt be perfected and finiſhed in this life. See <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. That <hi>we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly, in this preſent world; looking for the bleſſed Hope, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much more might be alleadged upon this accompt: <hi>Sed, Vivitur exigno ſi quis bene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit uti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we then to the Tranſpoſition and Application of this Propoſition; where firſt by way of Information, we may learn theſe Conſequents.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as the Spiritual Promiſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, are precious and ſweet-conditioned Covenants, ſo they are to fleſh and blood, without aſſiſting Grace, difficult and hard-conditioned Promiſes. But our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour told us aforehand, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14. <hi>That
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58489:24"/> ſtrait is the way, and narrow is the Gate, which leadeth unto life,</hi> and that there be few that enter in thereat; as did alſo his Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18. That the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall ſcarcely (that is, with much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty) be ſaved; where then ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appear?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may obſerve what need we have of a Saviour, that ſhould be God as well as Man; and that as in other regards, ſo to redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie or renew us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf, a peculiar people, zealous of good works, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. See alſo the end for which he gave himſelf, not onely to ſanctifie and waſh us with water through the Word; but alſo, that he might preſent us to himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, but that we ſhould be holy and without blemiſh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. Hence it is that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. <hi>Happy art thou, O</hi> Iſrael; <hi>who is like unto thee, O people! ſaved by the Lord, the ſheild of thine help; and who is the ſword of thine excellency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, By way of Redargution, this firſt ſerves to controul their miſtake, who
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58489:25"/> conceive that it is ſufficient unto Salvation, for us to be holy and religious with any kinde or in any degree of holineſs; For <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks thus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3. [Are ye ſo fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh? having begun in the ſpirit, are ye made perfect in the fleſh?] <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. He ſaith, That the Lord chaſtneth us to make us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his own holineſs; and the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. commanding us to be holy, as the Lord is holy, doth preſcribe both the true kinde and right degree of holineſs, for which we ſhould labor; at which alſo the Apoſtle aims when he prayeth thus, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12,13. [And the Lord make you to increaſe and abound in love one towards an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and towards all men, even as we do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you; to the end he may eſtabliſh your hearts unblameable in holineſs before God, even our Father, at the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with all his Saints.] Yea, the eternal life it ſelf, to which we are choſen in Chriſt Jeſus, is principally the perfection of holy love, as we heard before out of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. Which thing alſo <hi>David</hi> affirms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.3. For there he commanded the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58489:25"/> bleſſing, and life for evermore. Secondly, If any <hi>Athenians</hi> in our days, ſhould ask as thoſe did in former times, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.19. [May we know what this new Doctrine, whereof thou ſpeakeſt, is?] St <hi>John</hi> the Beloved Diſciple will give them ſatisfaction therein, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.7,8. [Brethren, I write no new Commandment unto you, but an old Commandment which ye had from the beginning; the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment is the Word which ye have heard from the beginning. Again, a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment I write unto you, which is true in him and in you, becauſe the darkneſs is paſt and the true light now ſhineth,] 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> Verſ. 5, 6. [Now I beſeech thee Lady, not as though I wrote a new Commandment unto thee; but that which we had from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, namely, that we love one another. And this is love, that we walk after his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: This is the Commandment, that as ye have heard from the beginning, ye ſhould walk in it.] Thirdly, It ſerves to anſwer many Cavils and Objections made by ſcrupulous men.</p>
            <p>As firſt, Is not this Popery, becauſe the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58489:26"/> Papiſts hold Perfection? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Though the Papiſts want no Errors, yet they hold there is one God, a Trinity of Perſons, Two Natures in Chriſt's own Perſon, his Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Office, his Twofold Eſtate of Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Exaltation, and many more Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and Primitive Heads of Doctrine: But nothing ought to be called or accounted Popiſh, which was taught by the Prophets, the Apoſtles, and Chriſt himſelf, as this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was both clearly and frequently held forth by all of them.</p>
            <p>But is it not <hi>Pelogian</hi> Doctrine? Indeed <hi>Pelagius</hi> taught, That man could of himſelf fulfil the Law of God; to whom <hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſwereth, Let him adde theſe words, That he can do it by the Grace of God, and we conſent.</p>
            <p>But is it not <hi>Arminianiſm?</hi> No; for <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> held the contrary, and herein are they <hi>Arminions</hi> who are otherwiſe minded.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It ſerves to check and overthrow their Error, who affirm the Law of God to be impoſſible to be fulfilled by the Saints in this life, though aſſiſted by the Grace and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58489:26"/> Spirit of Chriſt; who alſo do uſually for that end affix and attribute ſuch a rigor to the Law, as the Lord hath no where aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto it. For not onely the Apoſtles, but Chriſt himſelf doth affirm, That the whole requiring of the Law, yea, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets alſo, is fulfilled in the love aforeſaid, ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.38,39. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8,9. [Ow no man any thing, but to love one another; for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the Law. For this, Thou ſhalt not commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Thou ſhalt not kill, Thou ſhalt not ſteal, Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs, Thou not covet; and if there be any other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, it is briefly comprehended in this ſaying, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbor as thy ſelf: Therefore love is the fulfilling of the Law.] See <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13,14. Nor let any Reply that here the Apoſtle ſpeaks onely of the Commandments of the ſecond Table; for the true love of our Neighbor, is always founded in the love of God. And as this laſt preſuppoſeth the former, ſo the love of God is accompanied with the love of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.5. [But whoſo keepeth the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58489:27"/> Word of God, in him is the love of God perfected.] 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1,2. [Whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, is born of God; and every one that loveth him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, loveth him alſo that is begotten of him. By this we know, that we love the Children of God, when we love God and keep his Commandments.] Now if this were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be done, the Law of God were <hi>eo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> unjuſt and tyrannical: For <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is condemned by God and man, for laying ſuch commands upon the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as they could not poſſibly perform, <hi>Exod</hi> 5.6,7.</p>
            <p>For the further refuting of this opinion, we might produce the contrary judgment of all the Greek and Latin Fathers; of which take theſe few for the preſent, <hi>Justin Martyr, in Quaeſt. &amp; Reſponſ, ad Orthodoxos.</hi> But what is the total Juſtice or Univerſal Righteouſneſs according to the Law? To love God above himſelf, and his neighbor as himſelf, which is not impoſſible to men who apply their hearts thereunto; for that ſaying, By the works of the Law, ſhall no fleſh be juſtified; The Apoſtle doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58489:27"/> alleadge it, becauſe we cannot do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible things, but becauſe we will not do that which is poſſible. Do not blame the Lord, for he demands nothing impoſſible, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt de Paenit. Hom.</hi> 8 See <hi>Baſil</hi> upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>Hieronymus in Expoſ. Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol. ad Damaſum. Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. Nor would God command this, if it were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done of man: <hi>Idem de tempore, Serm.</hi> 61. Neither could God command any thing which is impoſſible, becauſe he is juſt; nor will he condemn any man for that he could not do, becauſe he is pious and good. <hi>Idem de tempore, Serm.</hi> 191. We deteſt their Blaſphemy, who ſay, That God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded any thing that is impoſſible to man. <hi>Concilium Arauſicanum,</hi> according to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith we believe, That all who are baptized, having received Grace, may and ought, by the help and the co-operation of Chriſt, to fulfil all things that belong to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if they will faithfully endeavor or labor thereunto.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By way of Correction, this ſerves firſt to reprove all unbelief that is found in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58489:28"/> men to the contrary, ſee what the Lord ſaith of the unbelieving <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who were ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unbelieving perſons, who were indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to enter upon the holy Land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, being deterred by the pretenders of impoſſibility to overcome the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and ſcale and beat down their Cities, <hi>Numbers</hi> 13 and 14 Chapters. Unto whom ſware the Lord, that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, but to them who believed not? So then they could not enter in, becauſe of unbelief, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.18,19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This ſerves to reprehend them who look for Life and the bleſſing of the Promiſes, and yet ſtand at a ſtay, and make not progreſs towards perfection. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Be watchful and ſtrengthen the things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, that are ready to die; for I have not ſound thy works perfect before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It rebukes them that go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rather then forward. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.4,5. <hi>Nevertheleſs, I have ſomething againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love. Remember therefore from whence thou art faln, and do thy firſt works, or I will come unto thee quickly,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58489:28"/> and will remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, They are here condemned who expect the bleſſings of Gods Promiſes and Covenants, and yet are ſo far from perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Obedience and Sanctification, that they never as yet did ſet one foot forward in that way; to thoſe the Lord ſpeaketh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant into thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and caſteſt my words behinde thee?</hi> Theſe although they haply call Chriſt their Lord and Saviour, and plead that they have eaten and drank at his Table, and that he hath taught in their ſtreets, yea that they have propheſied in his Name, will have this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer returned by him, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity, I know</hi> or own <hi>you not,</hi> Matth. 7.24,25. Luke 13.26,27. For <hi>unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe that are contentious, and do not obey the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruth, and obey unrighteouſneſs, ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and wrath, Tribulation and anguiſh upon overy ſoul that doth evil, upon the Jew firſt, and alſo upon the Gentile, Rom.</hi> 2.8,9.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58489:29"/>
            <p>Laſtly, This ſharply ſmites all thoſe of <hi>Michals</hi> ſpirit, who was a mocker at Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the name fignifieth, <hi>viz. Who is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect?</hi> For ſhe not onely deſpiſed <hi>David</hi> in her heart, for wearing the embleme of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but for dancing and rejoycing before the Ark; wherefore ſhe is puniſhed with barrenneſs, as all they ſhall be with ſterility of Grace, who remain ſuch ſcoffers of goodneſs, and mockers of perfection, ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20,21,22,23.</p>
            <p>In the fourth place, this Doctrine may ſerve for Exhortation; Firſt, To thoſe who have made ſome beginnings of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs towards Perfection, that they be careful to proceed on in that way, even unto Perfection. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Therefore leaving the principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, let us go on unto perfection. Moſes</hi> witneſſeth that the work of the Lord is perfect, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.4. And we are commanded to be perfect, as he is perfect, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48. <hi>The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day, Prov.</hi> 4.18. Wherefore let all that have obtained like precious Faith
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58489:29"/> with the Apoſtle and Saints of God; giving all diligence to add to their Faith, Vertue; and to Vertue, Knowledge; and to Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Temperance; and to Temperance, Patience; and to Patience, Godlineſs; and to Godlineſs, Brotherly kindneſs; and to Brotherly kindneſs, Love; for if theſe things be in you, and abound, they ſhall make you that ye ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. See <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.11. He that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill; and he that is holy, holy ſtill. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Wherefore my Beloved, as ye have always obeyed, not as in my preſence onely, but now much more in my abſence, work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling.</hi> Heb. 6.11,12. <hi>And we deſire that every one of you do ſhew the ſame diligence to the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Hope unto the end: That ye be not ſlothful, but followers of them who through faith and patience inherit the Promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To excite thoſe who never yet begun any advance towards holineſs, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things. Firſt, Whether the Jewels held forth in the precedent Promiſes, be not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58489:30"/> rich and precious merchandiſe; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at what price they muſt be purchaſed and had, if we will have them; for the Lord will ſpeak here unto us, as he did unto the Jews, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.12. <hi>If ye think good, give me my price; if not, forbear.</hi> And as the Lord did ſpeak to ſome, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Why ſtand ye here idle all the day?</hi> So will he ſay to thoſe, Awake to righteouſneſs, and ſin not; for ſome have not the knowledge of God; I ſpeak this to your ſhame.</p>
            <p>Confider, I pray you, what a deal of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you have to do, ere you can enjoy the Promiſes, and how little time ſome of you may have to do it in. And therefore pray with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 39.13. <hi>O ſpare me, that I may recover ſtrength before I go hence, and be no more.</hi> And with <hi>Moſes, Pſal.</hi> 90.12. <hi>So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> Is it a time to receive money, and to receive Garments, and Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and Vineyards, and Sheep, and Oxen, and Men-ſervants, and Maid-ſervants? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.16. [Wherefore he ſaith, Awake thou that ſleepeſt, ſtand up from the dead, and Chriſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58489:30"/> ſhall give thee light. See then that ye walk circumſpectly, not as fools, but as wiſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time, becauſe the days are evil. Wherefore be ye not unwiſe, but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what the will of the Lord is,] <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.14,15,16,17. [Repent therefore and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out, when the time of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord,] <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. [Whatſoever thine hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might; for there is no work, nor deviſe, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave whither thou goeſt,] <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. [Little children, let no man deceive you; he that doth righteouſneſs is righteous, as he is righteous; he that committeth ſin, is of the Devil; for the Devil ſinned from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For this purpoſe was the Son of God manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the work of the Devil,] 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7,8. [This I ſay therefore and teſtifie in the Lord, that ye henceforth walk not as other Gentiles walk, in the vanity of their minde, having their underſtanding darkned, being alienated from the Life of God, through the ignorance that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58489:31"/> is in them, through the hardneſs of their hearts; who being paſt feeling, have given over themſelves unto laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs: But ye have not ſo learned Chriſt, if ſo be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him as the truth is in Chriſt, That ye put off con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former converſation, the old-man which is corrupt <hi>(or deſtroying)</hi> according to the deceitful luſts, and be ye renewed in the ſpirit of your minde; and that ye put on the new man which is created after the Image of God in righteouſneſs, and holineſs of truth.] <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.17,18,19,20,21,22.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, This may ſerve for the comfort and encouragement of thoſe that deſire to obtain the Promiſes, and apply themſelves with all diligence to fulfil the Conditions of the ſame. For firſt it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the Conditions are feaſible, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Promiſes were made void: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Chriſt hath promiſed two things unto us of the greateſt conſequence and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>: Firſt, That if we finde our ſelves weary with ſtriving againſt ſin, and heavy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58489:31"/> laden therewith, that he will eaſe us by helping us to ſhake it off, and remove it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That we ſhall finde his yoke eaſie, and his burden light; onely he requireth of us, That we ſhould learn of him, that he is lowly and meek, and then we ſhall finde reſt unto our ſouls. See <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28,29,30. Whereunto his beloved Diſciple bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of his own experience, ſaying, <hi>For this is the love of God, that we keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and his Commandments are not grievous. For whatſoever is born of God over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the world; and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our Faith. Who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt?</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3,4,5. There is then no bar or let to the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Commandments, but the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed world of ſin, which may be overcome by Faith in the Son of God; and then Gods Commandments ſhall not be grievous, but delightful unto us: For what is eaſier or more delightful then to love? and therefore this burden of Chriſts which he lays upon us, is both light and ſweet in general, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58489:32"/> 19.10. alſo 119.103. There is nothing that unites us more cloſely to God then love. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35,36,37,38. Nothing is ſtronger and more victorious, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6,7. Nothing is crowned with more vertues, nor more omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent in the Lord; ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <p>Thus of the Duty to be done, Perfecting holineſs; now concerning the way wherein it is to be accompliſhed or acquired, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the fear of God. Which words may be three ways underſtood.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Of that Obedience to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments which is commonly called <hi>The fear of God. Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 112.1. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 12.13. In which way the Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make us an holy people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17,18,19. <hi>Thou haſt avouched the Lord this day to be thy God, and to walk in his ways, and to keep his Statutes and his Commandments, and his Judgments, and to hearken to his voice. And the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar people, as he hath promiſed thee; and that thou ſhouldſt keep all his Command<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments; and to make thee high above all Nations,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58489:32"/> which he hath made in praiſe, in name, and in honor, that thou maiſt be an holy people unto the Lord thy God, as he hath ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The fear of God may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of a reverend and awful fear of Gods Righteouſneſs and Judgments. And ſo it is the poſture we ſhould always ſtand in, while we are in our Chriſtian race towards Perfection. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Work out your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling:</hi> Which fear, when perfect love is come, is ſet aſide. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.17,18. For <hi>perfect love casteth out fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It may be taken for a filial or conjugal fear of God and his goodneſs. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Afterward ſhall the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>return and ſeek the Lord their God, and</hi> David <hi>their King, and ſhall fear the Lord, and his goodneſs in the latter days.</hi> And this fear, as it is love in ſome good meaſure and degree, ſo it is the way to that perfect love, which is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law: For the beginning, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, and perfecting whereof, I crave leave to ſpeak a word or two to my Reverend Brethren of the Miniſtry, by way of <hi>Aviſa</hi> from this <hi>Proviſo;</hi> And I hope that I may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58489:33"/> ſay with <hi>Paul, That I my ſelf alſo am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of you my Brethren, that ye alſo are full of goodneſs, filled with all knowledge, and able al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to admoniſh one another: Nevertheleſs, I have written the more boldly unto you in ſome ſort, as putting you in minde, becauſe of the Grace that is given to me of God, Rom.</hi> 15.14,15. It is not unknown to you how <hi>Phineas,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Eleazer,</hi> (that is, as the name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, Confidence of face in or from Gods help) obtained the Covenant of Peace, and of the Everlaſting Prieſthood, to wit, by ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Cozbi,</hi> the lie or lying nature of Sin, and <hi>Zimri,</hi> or that diſpoſition that rejoyceth therein. <hi>Num.</hi> 25.6,7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.30,31. Nor, that if we will be Gods mouth, we muſt take away the precious from the vile, <hi>Jere.</hi> 15.19. Nor, that we muſt ſtand in the Council of the Lord, ere we can practiſe and hear his words, <hi>Jere.</hi> 23.18. and much more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can turn men from the evil way, and from the evil of their doings, Verſe 22. Yea, that the Law of Truth was in <hi>Levi</hi>'s mouth, and iniquity was not found in his lips, and that he walked with God in peace and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58489:33"/> when he turned many away from iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.6. Onely mine earneſt Prayer to God for my ſelf and you is, That whereas the Spies and Searchers out of the promiſed Land, were of different mindes, and did in concluſion run two contrary courſes; <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> following the Lord fully, as himſelf teſtifieth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.24. and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the people to obey the Lord, to ſtand firm in the Faith, and ſo to ſet upon their enemies with courage, and hope of victory; but the other ten degenerating from the Faith and Obedience of God, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thouſands after them by their pretence of difficulties, yea, of impoſſibility to ſubdue the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and to take poſſeſſion of the promiſed Inheritance: That none of us may be found in the number of the laſt named, but all of us in the firſt, though the ſmaleſt number; for our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, That little of this Faith (that God will avenge his elect on their ſpiritual enemies) ſhall be found upon the Earth at his coming, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.6,7,8.</p>
            <p>And mine humble ſuit unto you all is, firſt,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58489:34"/> That ſeeing God giveth ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers for the perfecting of the Saints, and the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, till we all come in the unity of the Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt; that none of us diſcourage or retard the Saints in their progreſs, by any pretended impoſſibility as thoſe formerly did, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10,11,12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whereas Verſe 14. the Apoſtle henceforth would have no men, and much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs us, to be children toſſed too and fro with every wind of Doctrine, by the cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of men, whereby they lie in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: That we take heed that we ſuffer not the Authors whom we read, to impoſe upon us in this or any other kinde: To the Law, and to the Teſtimony; if they ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that, it is becauſe there is no light nor morning in them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.20.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To remember that the Apoſtle willeth, that we ſpeaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things, which is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58489:34"/> the Head, even Chriſt, from whom the whole Body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the Body, to the edifying of it ſelf in love, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15,16. For the end of the Law and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is love out of a pure heart and a good conſcience, and of faith unfained, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That with St <hi>Paul</hi> we preach Chriſt in the Saints, the Hope of Glory; warning every man, and teaching every man in all wiſdom, that we may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.27,28.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That we pray earneſtly under Hope, for the perfecting of the Saints, as the Apoſtles, and holy Miniſters of Chriſt did, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14,21. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 4.12. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, That neither the weak Brother may judge the ſtrong, nor the ſtrong may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the weak; ſeeing we muſt all appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgment ſeat of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58489:35"/>
            <p>Finally, Let us all follow the counſel of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1,2,3,4. and pray for one another, as the Apoſtle doth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20,21. for there are many Adverſaries.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
